<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: School | io.zack.io]]></title>
  <link href="http://io.zack.io/blog/categories/school/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://io.zack.io/"/>
  <updated>2017-04-12T12:43:24-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://io.zack.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Zack Sheppard]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Notes on My Beginner Dev Environment]]></title>
    <link href="http://io.zack.io/blog/2014/06/17/notes-on-my-beginner-dev-environment/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-17T21:08:15-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://io.zack.io/blog/2014/06/17/notes-on-my-beginner-dev-environment</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This post is a quick list of some of the things I&rsquo;m doing to help me code and learn during my time at <a href="http://flatironschool.com/">The Flatiron School</a>. Shoutout to <a href="https://twitter.com/waferbaby">Dan Bogan</a> who runs <a href="http://usesthis.com/">The Setup</a>. I got the idea for the post from reading his site for years.</p>

<h3>.bash_profile</h3>

<p>I&rsquo;ve used Terminal quite a bit over the last few years, at times even to manipulate servers at companies I worked at. But I&rsquo;ve never felt very at home there both because it was unfamiliar and because it&rsquo;s confusing to know what was going on if you don&rsquo;t use it frequently.</p>

<p>I made some cosmetic changes to a make it feel more like mine and make it a place I&rsquo;m excited about hanging out in all day. I also made some functional changes that I think are better suited for someone that is just getting started programming. When first starting out learning to code there are so many little things you can get wrong. I wanted to minimize the possibility that it&rsquo;s not working because I&rsquo;m in the wrong folder or some other small thing about the parts around my code so I could focus on the code itself. The things I changed about the prompt (so far) are:</p>

<ul>
<li>I modified the command line into a 3 line format to have a single line across the top so I can easily find my place for those times when 12 screens of text go swooping by and you want to find where it started. This is small but again I think these small things that make you feel less lost are helpful when you&rsquo;re eyes aren&rsquo;t used to scanning all that text.</li>
<li>Print out the full path so I always know where I&rsquo;m at in the file system. This was important for me especially while I&rsquo;m getting used to the command line because I didn&rsquo;t have the skill to just keep where I am in the file system in my head. It&rsquo;s getting easier already though and I might not need this much longer.</li>
<li>Because the directory can get long I have the prompt on it&rsquo;s own line which is actually really nice and clean. It&rsquo;s also great for copy/pasting commands.</li>
<li>In addition to showing the git branch I also made it so the branch name is red if it&rsquo;s dirty and green if it&rsquo;s clean to remind me to commit often. (link to )
<img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5497/14261841518_9ba0b709cf_b.jpg" alt="git-color" /></li>
<li>After a couple weeks I added a calm emoji bear on that hangs out on the right. It&rsquo;s a small thing but I think these small things that are a little fun to make this new environment are really great and helpful to make the termainal more cozy. If you&rsquo;re a 7th level blackbelt DB admin you might only need <code>$</code> but I am happy to have my cozy little prompt.</li>
</ul>


<h4>I also made these other small changes to .bash_profile</h4>

<ul>
<li>A few aliases to directories I use a lot like <code>flat3</code> (for my flatiron/week3 directory), <code>flat4</code>, etc.
<img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3894/14261960917_49d414b698_b.jpg" alt="flat3" /></li>
<li>A <a href="http://brettterpstra.com/2014/05/10/bash-and-dash/">function</a> to pull up documentation via <a href="http://kapeli.com/dash">dash</a> from the command line (Which I finally bought, it was totally worth it.)</li>
</ul>


<p>Lastly I increased the font to 16pt and installed the excellent <a href="http://ethanschoonover.com/solarized">Solarized</a> color scheme on Terminal and Sublime Text. The colors are cozy, I can look at them all day, and because there is less contrast between the colors they reduce eye strain.</p>

<h3>Notes</h3>

<p>Evernote is my go to for notes of all kinds. I can make notes and they are available wherever I go including on my commute. If you use it with the Chrome clipper extension you can clip entire pages (like the method documentation, hint hint!) and read them anywhere. I use 2 folders &ldquo;Flatiron Notes&rdquo; &amp; &ldquo;Flatiron Reading&rdquo;</p>

<p>Evernote isn&rsquo;t great for code though so I&rsquo;m also experimenting with adding a lessons_learned.md to my assignments. I&rsquo;ve been trying to do a recap instead of just going on to the next thing so for the last couple assignments after I save and push to git I rewind the changes with Cmd+Z, then go forward through them using Shift+Cmd+Z. At each point where i remember making a break through i copy that, and make a note about what i was thinking and what i learned. This isn&rsquo;t optimal, if you change somethig you can no longer Shift+Cmd+Z forward and have to restore from master. I might start adding the file to my .gitignore since I get all deep sometimes and it might be weird to let people see me talk to myself.</p>

<h3>Email</h3>

<p>Lastly becuase the deluge of Github emails is overwhelming when you first start using it I have a few filters that put some things in the Inbox and some right in a Github folder. I&rsquo;m not sure all of them are really exactly right yet but the one that saves the most Inbox space is, if it says &ldquo;[GitHub] Subscribed to&rdquo; in the subject line it goes right to the Github folder.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My First Post on Octopress]]></title>
    <link href="http://io.zack.io/blog/2014/06/11/my-first-post-on-octopress/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-11T07:15:22-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://io.zack.io/blog/2014/06/11/my-first-post-on-octopress</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hello World</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
